DAN KLEIN: All right.
So how are we going to solve
a tree structured CSP?
We can't just break it into two
pieces like we did with
independence sub problems.
OK, here's an algorithm for
a tree structured CSP.
The first step is to take this
tree structure and order it.
What does that mean?
It means you pick a root variable.
Any variable works.
So you grab this CSP by some root
variable, and you kind of pick it up
by its ankle, and let everything
else hang down.
OK, now you've got the CSP starting
at some variable, and there's a
direction to it.
Everything else is below, and
according to some order.
And we end up with some linear order,
and there are multiple choices.
And here is a linearization starting
at A, and you'll notice that all of
these constraints, which do not have
direction, have been replaced
by arcs which do.
It's still the same CSP, but these
directed arcs are going to help me
think about something very much
like arc consistency.
OK, so here is an ordering, starting at
A, and linearizing with that CSP.
Let's imagine we're still
in map coloring.
OK, very important.
Most CSPs are not map coloring.
Most constraints are not inequality
constraints, but that
is our running example.
So let's say these are the domains.
So for whatever reason, unary
constraints or whatever, these are the
domains at this point in time.
And we can put those domains
over here vertically.
So red and blue below A are
its remaining domains.
So we'd like to solve this CSP,
and it's tree structured.
We've ordered it.
Step two is to do a removal pass.
That's a lot like arc consistency.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to visit each arc once, and
we're going to make that
arc consistent.
How do we make it consistent?
The way we always make it consistent,
which is we pull the arc over, we
check to see what's in its trunk, and
we cross things off if needed.
All right, so let's do that here.
Let's actually make these
arcs consistent.
So the way we'll do this is we will
start with F, and we will
work our way leftward.
When we visit F, we're going to
say what arc comes into you?
How many arcs can come into F?
One, because it's a three.
Very important.
So I look at the arc coming into F. It's
D to F. And I look in its trunk.
So I look in D, and I say are there any
values in D which are guaranteed
to create a constraint violation?
And I say, well, at D, if I assigned
blue, I'd be in trouble.
So let's remove that.
All right.
Now the arc coming into F, D to
F has been made consistent.
Now we go to E. We look at the arc
coming into E. So that's D to E, and I
say, are there any values at D that
guarantee a constraint violation?
And it looks pretty good.
If I choose red, I'll be able
to choose anything.
If I choose green, I'll still
have the option of blue.
So now that arc is also consistent.
Now I go to D. What arc comes into D?
Well, it's B to D. So I look
at B to D, and I say do I
need to remove anything?
No.
I look at the arc coming into C. That's
B to C, and I see that if B
were assigned green, I'd be toast,
so let's remove green.
Now I look at the arc coming
into B, which is A to B.
And I see that blue has
to be removed there.
All right, so what have we done?
We have not done the full algorithm
for enforcing arc consistency.
We have not visited nodes over and
over again with a whole queue.
We have enforced the consistency of
arcs in a very particular pattern,
starting essentially at the right
and working leftward.
Now, the question is, is that enough?
Well, let's see what happens, and then
we'll see whether or not it's enough.
The next step after we've order
these nodes, we've done a
removal pass going backwards.
Now we do an assignment
pass going forward.
So we started A, and we
go left to right.
And we assign in any way we like.
Let's see what happens.
So I look at A, and it's only got one
choice left, so I'll take it.
Now I go to B. Is it possible
that I'm in trouble?
Is it possible that I've just made a
choice at A, such that at B I will
have no options left?
Well, it's not, because this
arc is consistent.
That's what consistency means.
The troublesome thing at
A, blue, got removed.
So what it means to say that A B is
currently consistent is whatever I
picked, including red, has an extension,
and I'll take one.
So I take blue.
And whatever I did at B, now I can
move on to C and I know I'm safe.
So when I get to C, I'll
pick something.
And so far, there's not
a lot of choice.
Now I get to D, I've actually
got a choice.
And what I choose, it may not be that
everything is safe, but I chose
something at B. The arc from B to D is
consistent, and so whatever I chose at
B has an extension.
All right.
To keep it interesting,
I will choose green.
Now I get to E, you see I can't choose
anything at E, but I'm guaranteed
something by the consistency of the
D to E arc, so I choose it.
And then again, I choose this here.
And it turns out that this algorithm
guarantees you that in this forward
assignment phase, there will always be
a consistent solution at each point.
You'll pick it and you'll move on,
which means no backtracking.
And so this whole thing was
pretty efficient, right?
What was the run time?
Well, I did something to
each arc going left.
And I did something to
each arc going right.
And so basically, it's order n from
the fact that I visit each arc a
constant number of times.
And at each arc, what did I do?
Well, I looked at all the pairs of
domain values in the head and the
tail, and then I checked
whether they're OK.
That's D squared.
So it's a linear algorithm,
just like I promised.
Now there's this important question,
which is am I sure it was enough to
just kind of enforce consistency
of the arcs once?
I have worries, like that so
I should prove something.